PROFESSOR: So just remember
what CSPs are.
They are a subclass of search problems,
but they're an important
class of problems in their own right.
A CSP is defined by a
set of variables.
Each variable has a set of values it
can take on called its domain, and
then in addition to variables taking on
values in the domain, there's a set
of constraints which describe the
configurations of the variable
assignments which are acceptable.
Constraints can come in two forms.
They can either be implicit, meaning
there's a little snippet of code that
you execute to see whether or not the
constraint is satisfied, or explicit,
where you actually enumerate the legal
tuples that you're willing to have in
the constraint.
So in the case that we looked at last
time, we had a recurring example of
map coloring.
And so here's a CSP for map coloring,
and each variable
might represent a country.
The domains are the colors we might
use, so in the simplified version,
red, green, and blue.
And the constraints might be the two
adjacent countries that touch on the
map can't have the same color.
That's an implicit constraint, and an
explicit constraint would say these
two variables can either be red/green,
blue/green, and so on.
Constraints come in multiple arities.
They can be unary, meaning they impose
constraints on one variable at a time;
binary, meaning two variables
at a time--
these inequality constraints are
binary constraints; or n-ary.
For example, we might have five
variables that are mutually
constrained, and that would be
a degree five constraint.
The goal from a constraint satisfaction,
as we've been talking
about in this class, is to find some
solution-- meaning to find some
assignment to the variables which
assigns a value to every variable and
meets all of the constraints.
You could imagine doing other things,
but the algorithms we're presenting
here don't do these things.
For example, find all the solutions,
find the best solution according to
some scoring function.
Here, we're just looking to
find some legal solution.
We had a basic mechanism for solving
these called backtracking search,
which is really just a variant
of depth-first search.
In this particular case, the
implementation in the
pseudo code is recursive.
But in terms of the computation it
performs, that computation is just
like depth-first search.
It starts at the top of the search tree,
and at the top of the search
tree, you have no variables assigned.
And then you recurse, assigning
one variable at a time.
In a naive depth-first search, all you
know is two things about a state.
Does it have successors--
which everything that's not a complete
assignment has successors--
and is it a goal?
So you don't know whether or not you
have a goal until you get to the very
end at the bottom of the tree when
all variables are assigned.
This recursive backtracking search has a
big innovation in that it can detect
when a constraint is already violated.
That means not only does this state
not pass the goal test, but it
essentially doesn't have successors,
because it's already doomed.
So together, these ideas give this
algorithm recursive backtracking
search that we've presented last time,
and there were a couple question
marks, like what order should
we work on the variables?
When we have a variable in front of
us, which values should we try, in
what order, and so on?
But essentially, you do a depth-first
search until you find a solution, or
you exhaust all options.
In order to improve backtracking
search, we had a couple general
purpose ideas that together and
individually give huge gains in speed.
But in the end, constraint
satisfaction is
still an NP-hard problem.
That means no matter how many of these
tricks we have, and how sophisticated
our CSP solvers are, there are still
going to be instances that, to the
best of our knowledge, are going
to be extremely hard.
So what can we do that, in general,
will these things up greatly?
Well, one idea is ordering.
Whenever we have a choice of what
variable to visit next in the depth
first procedure, we should be smart
about which variable we work on.
And the short version was, we decided
that if there are easy variables and
hard variables, where easy means there
are lots of values left in their
domains, and hard means they're very
heavily constrained and may only have
a few values left, we should work
on the hard variables first.
The reason we should work on the hard
variables first is because sooner or
later, you have to do
all the variables.
You might as well do the hard ones now
and get your backtracking out of the
way before you get too
deep into the tree.
On the other hand, when we're
considering the values that we're
going to try, you don't have
to try all the values.
If you get lucky with the first value,
you never have to try the others.
So you should try the values that
are most likely to work out.
And the way that we formulated that
as a heuristic here is the least
constraining value.
And the way we implement that is, we
consider the possible values to
assign, we look at their
effect on filtering--
so forward checking arc consistency--
and we choose the one that imposes
the least constraints.
Then there was filtering.
Filtering was this idea that we want
to detect inevitable failure early.
We had forward checking, which was a
very limited kind of look ahead, where
even beyond the variables we've
assigned, we check to see whether are
any constraint violations waiting
to happen in one step.
And then we had this notion of arc
consistency, where with arc
consistency, we have a much more
thorough check for future inevitable
failures, but it's still not perfect.
So we still had a backtracking search.
We're going to talk a little bit more
about arc consistency today, and then
we're going to talk about structure.
And the idea with structure is
sometimes, we can look at the
constraint graph, and we can see
something special there that lets us
speed up our solution.